Mss.497.3.J71
American Philosophical Society
Ojibwa ethnographic and linguistic field notes, 1903-1905
Mss.497.3.J71
American Philosophical Society
1.0 Volume(s) 1 volume, ca. 250 p.; 42 items
1 volume, ca. 250 p.; 42 items.
The collection includes material relating to government, mythology, festivals, customs, games, etc. of the Ojibwa Indians. Also includes comments on the language; vocabulary, some items with English glosses; lists of bands and locations; and photographs of people, activities, dwellings, canoes, etc.
Jones, William,1871-1909.
Box 1
Volume 1
Related Archival Materials note
Jones' major work on the Ojibwa was published posthumously by Truman Michelson, ed. Ojibwa Texts, 2 vols. (American Ethnological Society, 1917, 1919).
Immediate Source of Acquisition note
Presented by Ruth Landes (Dept. of Anthropology, McMaster University, 1280 Main Street, Hamilton, Ontario, Canada L8S 4L9) and accessioned, 12/--/1977 (2071ms).
Scope and Contents note
Native American Images note: 43 pencil sketches, 42 black and white silver gelatin photographs of Ojibwa Indians of Minnesota and Ontario taken by Jones from 1903-1905. Ethnographic images of pipes, canoes, traps, totem figures, pottery, birch bark dwellings, a cradleboard, and Native Americans in traditional dress. Primarily scenes from Nett Lake, Bois Fort, Minnesota and Lake Nipigon, Ontario. Referenced in the online Daythal Kendall Guide to Native American Collections at the American Philosophical Society.
Biographical/Historical note
William Jones was born on March 28, 1871, on a Sauk and Fox reservation in Kansas. He was educated in Indian schools in Kansas and Indiana, at Hampton Institute and Andover, and received a B.A. from Harvard in 1900. He continued anthropological studies at Columbia, where he received an M.A. in 1901 and a PhD in 1904. Jones conducted field work, in affiliation with the American Museum of Natural History, on Algonquian languages. He was killed by native Filipinos in March 1909, while on an ethnological expedition for the American Museum.
American Museum of Natural History.; Benedict, Ruth, 1887-1848; Boas, Franz, 1858-1942; Mead, Margaret,1901-1978,comp.; Algonquian Indians; Field notes.; Gelatin silver prints; Indians of North America--Languages; Indians of North America--Minnesota; Indians of North America--Ontario; Indians of North America--Religion; Indians of North America--Social life and customs; Ojibwa Indians; Sketches.
- Ojibwa canoes, 1903-1905; Number 4
- Ojibwa chief and wife, 1903-1905; Number 9
- Ojibwa family, 1903-1905; Number 9
- Ojibwa man, 1903-1905; Number 9
- Ojibwa mother and children, 1903-1905; Number 9
- Ojibwa totem figures, 1903-1905; Number 4
- Ojibwa utensils, 1903-1905; Number 4
- Ojibwa woman and child, 1903-1905; Number 9
- Ojibwas, 1903-1905; Number 9
- Ojibwas, 1903-1905; Number 9